<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C08"/>
  <longToken><p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p10"/>Every one adored Elizabeth.</longToken> If the servants had any request to make, <longToken>it was always through</longToken> <longToken>her intercession.</longToken> We were strangers to any species of disunion and dispute; for
  <longToken>although there was a great dissimilitude in our characters,</longToken> there was an harmony in that
  very dissimilitude. I was more calm and philosophical than my companion; yet my temper
  was not so yielding. My application was of longer endurance; but it was not so severe
  whilst it endured. I delighted in investigating the facts relative to the actual world;
  she busied herself in following the aërial creations of the poets. The world was to me a
  secret, which I desired to <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_060" n="048"/>discover; to her it was
  a vacancy, which she sought to people with imaginations of her own.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p10"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p11"/>My brothers were considerably younger than myself; but I had a friend in one of my
  schoolfellows, who compensated for this deficiency. Henry Clerval was the son <longToken>of a merchant of Geneva, an intimate friend of my father.</longToken> He was a boy of singular talent and
  <longToken>fancy. <del>I remember,</del> when he was nine years old, he wrote a fairy tale, which was the delight and amazement of all his companions.</longToken> His favourite study consisted in books of
  <longToken>chivalry and romance;</longToken> <longToken>and when very young, I can remember, that we used to act plays composed by him out of these favourite books, the principal characters of which were Orlando, Robin Hood, Amadis, and St. George.</longToken><p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p11"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p12"/>
  <del rend="margin_line">No youth could have passed more <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_061" n="049"/>happily than mine. My parents were indulgent, and my companions amiable. Our studies were never forced; and by some means we always had an end placed in view, which excited us to ardour in the prosecution of them. It was by this method, and not by emulation, that we were urged to application. Elizabeth was not incited to apply herself to drawing, that her companions might not outstrip her; but through the desire of pleasing her aunt, by the representation of some favourite scene done by her own hand. We learned Latin and English, that we might read the writings in those languages; and so far from study being made odious to us through punishment, we loved application, and our amusements would have been the labours of other children. Perhaps we did not read so many books, or learn languages so <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_062" n="050"/>quickly, as those who are disciplined according to the ordinary methods; but what we learned was impressed the more deeply on our memories.</del>
  <note resp="#MWS">bad</note>
  <add place="bottom">With what delight do I even now remember the details of our domestic circle, and the happy years of my childhood. Joy attended on my steps—and the ardent affection that attached me to my excellent parents, my beloved Elizabeth, and Henry, the brother of my soul, has given almost a religious and sacred feeling to the recollections of a period passed beneath their eyes, and in their society.</add>
  <p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p12"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p13"/>In this description of our domestic circle <longToken>I include Henry</longToken> Clerval; for he was
  constantly with us. He went to school with me, and generally passed the afternoon at our
  house: for being an only child, and destitute of companions at home, his <longToken>father was well pleased</longToken> that he should find associates at our house; and we were never completely happy
  when Clerval was absent.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p13"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p14"/>I feel pleasure in dwelling on the recollections of childhood, before misfortune had
  tainted my mind, and changed its bright visions of extensive usefulness into gloomy and
  narrow reflections upon self. But, in drawing the picture of my early days, I must not
  omit to record those events which led, by in<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_063" n="051"/>sensible steps to my after tale of misery: for when I would account to myself for the
  birth of that passion, which afterwards ruled my destiny, I find it arise, like a
  mountain river, from ignoble and almost forgotten sources; but, swelling as it
  proceeded, it became the torrent which, in its course, has swept away all my hopes and
  joys.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p14"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p15"/>Natural philosophy is the genius that has regulated my <longToken>fate; I desire therefore,</longToken> in
  this narration, to <del>state</del>
  <add>relate</add> those facts which led to my predilection for that science. When
  I was thirteen years of age, we all went on a party of pleasure to the baths near
  Thonon: the inclemency of the weather obliged us to remain a day confined to the inn. In
  this house I chanced to find a volume of the works of Cornelius Agrippa. I opened it
  with apathy; the theory which he attempts to demonstrate, and the <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_064" n="052"/>wonderful facts which he relates, soon changed this
  feeling into enthusiasm. A new light seemed to dawn upon my mind; and, bounding with
  joy, I communicated my discovery to my father. <del rend="strikethrough">I cannot help remarking here the many opportunities instructors possess of directing the attention of their pupils to useful knowledge, which they utterly neglect. My father looked</del>
  <longToken><add>who looking</add> carelessly at the title-page of my book,</longToken> <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> said, “Ah! Cornelius Agrippa! My dear Victor, do not waste your time upon
  this; it is sad trash.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p15"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p16"/>If, instead of this remark, my father had taken the pains to explain to me, that the
  principles of Agrippa had been entirely exploded, and that a modern system of science
  had been introduced, which possessed much greater powers than the ancient, because the
  powers of the latter were chimerical, while <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_065" n="053"/>those
  of the former were real and practical; under such circumstances, I should certainly have
  thrown Agrippa aside, and, with my imagination warmed as it <longToken>was, should probably have applied myself to the more rational theory of chemistry which has resulted from modern discoveries.</longToken> It is even possible, that the train of my ideas would never have received
  the fatal impulse that led to my ruin. But the cursory glance my father had taken of my
  volume by no means assured me that he was acquainted with its contents; and I continued
  to read with the greatest avidity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p16"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p17"/>When I returned home, my first care was to procure the whole works of this author, and
  afterwards of Paracelsus and Albertus Magnus. I read and studied the wild fancies of
  these writers with delight; they appeared to me trea<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_066" n="054"/>sures known to few <longToken>beside myself; and although I often wished to communicate these secret stores of knowledge to my father,</longToken> yet his indefinite censure of my
  favourite Agrippa always withheld me. I disclosed my discoveries to Elizabeth,
  therefore, under a <longToken>promise of strict secrecy;</longToken> but she did not interest herself in the
  subject, and I was left by her to pursue my studies alone.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p17"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p18"/>It may appear <longToken>very strange, that</longToken> a disciple of Albertus Magnus should arise in the
  eighteenth century; but our family was not scientifical, and I had <longToken>not attended any of the lectures given at the schools of Geneva.</longToken> My dreams were therefore undisturbed by
  reality; and I entered with the greatest diligence into the search of the philosopher’s
  stone and the elixir of life. But the latter obtained my <longToken>most undi<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_067" n="055"/>vided attention:</longToken> wealth was an inferior object; but what glory would
  attend the discovery, if I could banish disease from the human frame, and render man
  invulnerable to any but a violent death!<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p18"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p19"/>Nor were these my only visions. The raising of ghosts or devils was a promise liberally
  accorded by my favourite authors, the fulfilment of which I most eagerly sought; and if
  my incantations were always unsuccessful, I attributed the failure rather to my own
  inexperience <longToken>and mistake, than to a want of skill or fidelity</longToken> in my instructors.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p19"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p20"/>The natural phænomena that take place every day before our eyes did not escape my
  examinations. Distillation, and the wonderful effects of steam, processes of which my
  favourite authors were utterly ignorant, excited my astonishment; but my utmost wonder
  was <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_068" n="056"/>engaged by some <longToken>experiments on an air-pump,</longToken>
  which I saw employed by a gentleman whom we were in the habit of visiting.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p20"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p21"/>The ignorance of the early philosophers on these and several other points served to
  decrease their credit with me: but I could not entirely throw them aside, before some
  other system should occupy their place in my mind.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p21"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p22"/>When I was about fifteen years old, we had retired to our house near Belrive, when we
  witnessed <longToken>a most violent and terrible thunder-storm.</longToken> It advanced from behind the
  mountains of Jura; and the thunder burst at once with frightful loudness from various
  quarters of the heavens. I remained, while the storm lasted, watching its progress with
  curiosity and delight. As I stood at the door, on a sudden I beheld a stream of fire
  issue from an old and beautiful oak, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_069" n="057"/>which stood
  about twenty yards from our house; and so soon as the dazzling light vanished, the oak
  had disappeared, and nothing remained but a blasted stump. When we visited it the next
  morning, we found the tree shattered in a singular manner. It was not splintered by the
  shock, but entirely reduced to thin ribbands of wood. I never beheld any thing so utterly
  destroyed.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p22"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p23"/>The catastrophe of this tree excited my extreme astonishment; and I eagerly inquired of
  my father the nature and origin of thunder and lightning. He replied, “Electricity;”
  describing at the same time the various effects of that power. He constructed a small
  electrical machine, and exhibited a few experiments; he <longToken>made also a kite,</longToken> with a wire
  and string, which drew down that fluid from the clouds.<note resp="#MWS" cert="low">you said your family was not sientific.</note>
  <p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p23"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p24"/>This last stroke completed the overthrow <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_070" n="058"/>of
  Cornelius Agrippa, Albertus Magnus, and Paracelsus, who had so long reigned the lords of
  my imagination. But by some fatality I did not feel <longToken>inclined to commence the study of any modern system;</longToken> and this disinclination was influenced by the following
  circumstance.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p24"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p25"/>My father expressed a wish that I should attend a course of lectures upon natural
  philosophy, to which I <longToken>cheerfully consented.</longToken> Some accident prevented my attending <longToken>these lectures until the course was nearly finished. The lecture, being therefore one of the last, was entirely incomprehensible to me.</longToken> The professor discoursed with the greatest
  fluency of potassium and boron, of sulphates and oxyds, terms <longToken>to which I could affix no idea; and</longToken> I became disgusted with the science of natural philosophy, <longToken>although I still read <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_071" n="059"/>Pliny and Buffon with delight,</longToken> authors, in my
  estimation, of nearly equal interest and utility.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p25"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p26"/>My occupations at this age were principally the mathematics, and most of the branches
  of study appertaining to that science. I was busily employed in learning languages;
  Latin was already familiar to me, <longToken>and I began to read some of the easiest Greek authors without the help of a lexicon. I also perfectly understood English and German.</longToken> <longToken>This is the list of my accomplishments at the age of seventeen;</longToken> and you may conceive that my
  hours were fully employed in acquiring and maintaining a knowledge of this various
  literature.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p26"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p27"/>Another task also devolved upon me, when I became the instructor of my brothers. Ernest
  was six years younger than myself, and was my principal pu<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_072" n="060"/>pil. He had been afflicted with ill health from his infancy, through which
  Elizabeth and I had been his constant nurses: his disposition was gentle, <longToken>but he was incapable of any severe application.</longToken> William, the youngest of our family, was yet an
  infant, and the most beautiful little fellow in the world; his lively blue eyes, dimpled
  cheeks, and endearing manners, inspired the tenderest affection.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p27"/>
  <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p28"/>Such was our domestic circle, from which care and pain seemed for ever banished. My
  father directed our studies, and my mother partook of our enjoyments. Neither of us
  possessed the slightest pre-eminence over the other; the voice of command was never
  heard amongst us; but mutual affection engaged us all to comply with and obey the
  slightest desire of each other.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p28"/>
  <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="1"/>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="2"/>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_073" n="061"/>
   <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1"/> W<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1_hi1"/>HEN<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1_hi1"/> I had attained the age of seventeen, my parents
            resolved that I should <longToken>become a student at the university of Ingolstadt.</longToken> I had hitherto
            attended the schools of Geneva; but my father thought it necessary, for the completion
            of my education, that I should be made acquainted with other customs than those of my
            native country. My departure was therefore fixed at an early date; but, before the day
            resolved upon could arrive, the first misfortune of my life occurred—an omen, as it
            were, of my future misery. <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_074" n="062"/>Elizabeth had caught
            the scarlet <longToken>fever; but her illness was not severe, and she quickly recovered.</longToken> During her
            confinement, many arguments had been urged to persuade my mother to refrain from
            attending upon her. She had, at first, yielded to our entreaties; but when she heard
            that her favourite was recovering, she could no longer <longToken>debar herself from her society, and entered her chamber long before the danger of infection was past.</longToken> The consequences
            of this imprudence were fatal. On the third day my mother sickened; her fever was very
            malignant, and the looks of her attendants prognosticated the worst event. On her
            death-bed the fortitude and benignity of this <longToken><del>admirable</del> <add>amiable</add> woman</longToken> did not desert her. She
            joined the hands of Elizabeth and <longToken>myself: “My children,” she said, “my firmest hopes of future <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_075" n="063"/>happiness were placed on the prospect of your union. This expectation will now be the consolation of your father.</longToken> Elizabeth, my
  love, you must supply my place to <longToken>your younger cousins.</longToken> Alas! I regret that I am taken
            from you; and, happy and beloved as I have been, is it not hard to quit you all? But
            these are not thoughts befitting me; I will endeavour to resign myself cheerfully to
            death, and will indulge a hope of meeting you in another world.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p2"/>She died calmly; and her countenance expressed affection even in death. I need not
            describe the feelings of those whose dearest ties are rent by that most irreparable
            evil, the void that presents itself to the soul, and the despair that is exhibited on
            the countenance. It is so long before the mind can persuade itself that she, whom we saw
            every day, and whose very existence <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_076" n="064"/>appeared a
            part of our own, can have departed for ever—that the brightness of a beloved eye can
            have been extinguished, and the sound of a voice so familiar, and dear to the ear, can
            be hushed, never more to be heard. These are the reflections of the first days; but when
            the lapse of time proves the reality of the evil, then the actual bitterness of grief
            commences. Yet from whom has not that rude hand rent away some dear connexion; and why
            should I describe a sorrow which all have felt, and must feel? The time at length
            arrives, when grief is rather an indulgence than a necessity; and the smile that plays
            upon the lips, although it may be deemed <longToken>a sacrilege, is not banished.</longToken> My mother was
            dead, but we had still duties which we ought to perform; we must continue our course
            with the rest, and learn to think <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_077" n="065"/>ourselves
            fortunate, whilst one remains whom the spoiler has not seized.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p2"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p3"/>My journey to Ingolstadt, which had been deferred by these events, was now again
            determined upon. I <longToken>obtained from my father a respite of some weeks. This</longToken> period was
            spent sadly; my mother’s death, and my speedy departure, depressed our spirits; but
            Elizabeth endeavoured to renew the spirit of cheerfulness in our little society. Since
            the death of her aunt, her mind had acquired new firmness and vigour. She determined to
            fulfil her duties with the greatest exactness; and she felt that that most imperious
            duty, of rendering her uncle and cousins happy, had devolved upon her. She consoled me,
            amused her uncle, instructed my brothers; and I never <longToken>beheld her so enchanting as at this time, when she was continually endeavouring to con<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_078" n="066"/>tribute to the happiness of others, entirely forgetful of herself.</longToken><p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p3"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p4"/>The day of my departure at length arrived. <longToken>I had taken leave of all my friends, excepting Clerval, who spent the last evening with us.</longToken> He bitterly lamented that he was
            unable to accompany me: but his father could not be persuaded to part with <longToken>him, intending</longToken> that he should become a partner with him in business, in compliance with his
            favourite theory, that learning was superfluous in the commerce of ordinary life. Henry
            <del>had a refined mind; he had no desire to be idle, and was well pleased to become his father’s partner, but he believed that a man might be a very good trader, and yet possess a cultivated understanding.</del>
   <add>loved poetry and his mind was filled with the imagery and sublime sentiments of the masters of that art. A poet himself, he turned with <del-INNER>y</del-INNER> disgust from the details of ordinary life. His own <del-INNER>soul</del-INNER> mind was all the possession that he prized, beautiful &amp; majestic thoughts the only wealth he coveted—daring as the eagle and as free, common laws could not be applied to him; and while you gazed on him you felt his soul’s spark was more divine—more truly stolen from Apollo’s sacred fire, than the glimmering ember that animates other men.</add>
   <p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p4"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p5"/>We <longToken>sat late,</longToken> listening to his complaints, and making many little arrangements for the
            future. The next <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_079" n="067"/>morning early I departed. Tears
            gushed from the eyes of Elizabeth; they proceeded partly from sorrow at my departure,
            and partly because she reflected that the same journey was to have taken place three
            months before, when a mother’s blessing would have accompanied me.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p5"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p6"/>I threw myself into the chaise that was to convey me away, and indulged in the most
            melancholy reflections. I, who had ever been surrounded by amiable companions,
            continually engaged in endeavouring to bestow mutual pleasure, I was now alone. <longToken>In the university,</longToken> whither I was going, I must form my own friends, and be my own protector. My
            life had hitherto been remarkably secluded and domestic; and this had given me
            invincible repugnance to new countenances. I loved my brothers, Elizabeth, and <longToken>Clerval;</longToken>
  <longToken><pb xml:id="F1818_v1_080" n="068"/>these</longToken> were “old familiar faces;” but I believed
            myself totally unfitted for the company of strangers. Such were my reflections as I
            commenced my journey; but as I proceeded, my spirits and hopes rose. I ardently desired
            the acquisition of knowledge. I had often, when at home, thought it hard to remain
            during my youth cooped up in one place, and had longed to enter the world, and take my
            station among other human beings. Now my desires were complied with, and it would,
            indeed, have been folly to repent.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p6"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p7"/>I had sufficient leisure for these and many other reflections during my journey to
            Ingolstadt, which was long and fatiguing. At length the high white steeple of the town
            met my eyes. I alighted, and was conducted to my solitary apartment, to spend the
            evening as I pleased.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p7"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p8"/>
   <longToken><pb xml:id="F1818_v1_081" n="069"/>The next morning I delivered my letters of introduction,</longToken> and paid a visit to some of the principal professors, and among others to
            M. Krempe, professor of natural philosophy. He received me with politeness, and asked me
            several questions concerning my progress in the different branches of science
            appertaining to natural philosophy. <longToken>I mentioned, it is true, with fear and trembling, the only authors I had ever read upon those subjects.</longToken> The professor stared: “Have you,”
            he said, “really spent your time in studying such nonsense?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p8"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p9"/>I replied in the affirmative. “Every minute,” continued M. Krempe with warmth, “every
            instant that you have wasted on those books is utterly and entirely lost. You have
            burdened your memory with exploded systems, and useless names. Good God! in what <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_082" n="070"/>desert land have you lived, where no one was kind
            enough to inform you that these fancies, which you have so greedily imbibed, are a
            thousand years old, and as musty as they are ancient? I little expected in this
            enlightened and scientific age to find a disciple of Albertus Magnus and Paracelsus. My
            dear Sir, you must begin your studies entirely anew.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p9"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p10"/>So saying, he stept aside, and wrote down a list of several books treating of natural
            philosophy, which he desired me to procure, and dismissed me, after mentioning that in
            the beginning of the following week he intended to commence a course of lectures upon
            natural philosophy in its general relations, and that M. Waldman, a fellow-professor,
            would lecture upon chemistry the alternate days that he missed.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p10"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p11"/>I returned home, not disappointed, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_083" n="071"/>for I had long
            considered those authors useless whom the professor <longToken>had so strongly reprobated; but I did not feel much inclined to study the books which I procured at his recommendation.</longToken> M.
            Krempe was a little squat man, with a gruff voice and repulsive countenance; the
            teacher, therefore, did not prepossess me in favour of his doctrine. Besides, I had a
            contempt for the uses of modern natural philosophy. It was very different, when the
            masters of the science sought immortality and power; such views, although futile, were
            grand: but now the scene was changed. The <longToken>ambition of the inquirer</longToken> seemed to limit
            itself to the annihilation of those visions on which my interest in science was chiefly
            founded. I was required to exchange chimeras of boundless grandeur for realities of
            little worth.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p11"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p12"/>Such were my reflections during <longToken>the <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_084" n="072"/>first two or three days spent almost in solitude.</longToken> But as the ensuing week commenced, I thought of the
            information which M. Krempe had given me concerning the lectures. And although I could
            not consent to go and hear that little conceited fellow deliver sentences <longToken>out of a pulpit,</longToken> I recollected what he had said of M. Waldman, whom I had never seen, as he had
            <longToken>hitherto been</longToken> out of town.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p12"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p13"/>Partly from curiosity, and partly from idleness, I went into the lecturing room, which
            M. Waldman entered shortly after. This professor was very unlike his colleague. He
            appeared <longToken>about fifty years of age, but with an aspect expressive of the greatest benevolence;</longToken> a few gray hairs covered his temples, but those at the back of his head
            were nearly black. His person was short, but remarkably erect; and his <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_085" n="073"/>voice the sweetest I had ever heard. He began his
            lecture by a recapitulation of the history of chemistry and the various improvements
            made by different men of <longToken>learning, pronouncing with fervour the names of the most distinguished discoverers.</longToken> He then took a cursory view of the present state of the
            science, and explained many of its elementary terms. After having made a few preparatory
            experiments, he concluded with a panegyric upon <longToken>modern chemistry,</longToken> the terms of which I
            shall never forget:—<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p13"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p14"/>“The ancient teachers of this science,” said he, “promised impossibilities, and
            performed nothing. The modern masters promise very little; they know that metals cannot
            be transmuted, and that the elixir of life is a chimera. But these philosophers, whose
            hands seem only made to dabble <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_086" n="074"/>in dirt, and their
            eyes to pour over the microscope or crucible, have indeed performed miracles. They
            penetrate into the recesses of nature, and shew how she works in her hiding places. They
            ascend into <longToken>the heavens;</longToken> they have discovered how the blood circulates, and the nature
            of the air we breathe. They have acquired new and almost unlimited powers; they can
            command the thunders of heaven, mimic the earthquake, and even mock the invisible world
            with its own shadows.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p14"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p15"/><longToken>I departed highly pleased with the professor and his lecture,</longToken> <longToken>and paid him a visit the same evening.</longToken> His manners in private were even more mild <longToken>and attractive than in public;</longToken>
            for there was a certain dignity in his mien during his lecture, <longToken>which in his own house was replaced by the greatest <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_087" n="075"/>affability and kindness.</longToken> He heard <longToken>with attention my little narration concerning my studies, and</longToken> smiled
            at the names of Cornelius Agrippa, and Paracelsus, but without the contempt that M.
            Krempe had exhibited. He said, that “these were men to whose indefatigable zeal modern
            philosophers were indebted for most of the foundations of their knowledge. They had left
            to us, as an easier task, to give new names, and arrange in connected classifications, the
            facts which they in a great degree had been the instruments of bringing to light. The
            labours of men of genius, however erroneously directed, scarcely ever fail in ultimately
            turning to the solid advantage of mankind.” I listened <del rend="strikethrough">to his statement, which was delivered</del>
   <add>to him with interest for he spoke</add> without <del rend="strikethrough">any</del> presumption or affectation; and then added, that his lecture had
            removed my prejudices against modern <longToken><pb xml:id="F1818_v1_088" n="076"/>chemists; and I, at the same time, requested</longToken> his advice concerning the books I ought to procure.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p15"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p16"/>“I am happy,” said M. Waldman, “to have gained a disciple; and if your application
            equals your ability, I have no doubt of your success. Chemistry is that branch of
            natural philosophy in which the greatest improvements have been and may be <longToken>made; it</longToken> is
            on that account that I have made it my peculiar study; but at the same time I have not
            neglected the other branches of science. A man would make but a very sorry chemist, if
            he attended to that department of human knowledge alone. If your wish is <longToken>to become really</longToken> a man of science, and not merely a petty experimentalist, I should advise you to
            apply to every branch of natural philosophy, including mathematics.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p16"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p17"/>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_089" n="077"/>He then took me into his laboratory, and
            explained to me the uses of his various machines; instructing me as to what I ought to
            procure, and promising me the use of his own, when I should have advanced far enough in
            the science not to derange their mechanism. He also gave me the list of books which I
            had requested; and I took my leave.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p17"/>
   <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p18"/>Thus ended a day memorable to <longToken>me: it decided my future destiny.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p18"/> <note resp="#MWS">If there were ever to be another edition of this book, I should re-write these two first chapters. The incidents are tame and ill-arranged—the language sometimes childish.—They are unworthy of the rest of the <del>w book</del>narration.</note> <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="2"/></longToken>
</xml>